"Refusing without Guilt"
I have a hard time refusing favors.
When someone asks a favor,
I reluctantly oblige even
when I don't want to.
The more others expect of me,
I try to fulfill their expectations.
Listening to your lectures,
I understand that I'm doing
this for their praise and approval.
I'd like to know
how to say no to others
without making them feel bad,
nor feeling bad myself.
Just do as you feel like.
(Audience) Laughter
I don't understand.
If you want to say no, just say no.
If you feel uncomfortable
doing so,accept the favor.
Don't take it too seriously.
Reason being - whether
you refuse or accept,
it's ultimately for your own sake,
not for the other person's sake.
Refusing the favor will make
the other person feel bad.
If the other person feels bad,
he/she will think badly of you.
You ultimately can't refuse
as you want everyone
to have a favorable stance towards you.
And yet to accept all favors,
you can't handle the consequences.
(Sunim) Either way you're making
the decision for your own good.
Hence is it really
an unconditional self-sacrifice
on your part to accept favors?
It is not.
It in itself bases on
your own selfishness.
You selfishly want everyone to
always say good things about you.
You're basing your decision on
your self-interest either way.
If you give up your selfishness,
you can both accept
or reject with a peace of mind.
If you can't give up your selfishness,
just accept favors while
bearing the discomfort.
In any case, the decision is
based on selfishness.
It's not like one is
based on selfishness
while the other is
based on self-sacrifice.
Both are based on selfishness.
And yet you think
refusing favors is selfish,
accepting favors is altruistic.
This delusion generates conflict
between selfishness
and altruism for you.
Once you realize both are
based on your own selfishness,
it doesn't matter which you choose.
If you refuse the favor,
you will lose face.
If you accept the favor,
you will lose your time and energy.
As you want to hold onto both,
you are having difficulty.
Hence you are asking me
how to slyly refuse favors
without losing face, are you not?
(Audience) Laughter
There can be a bit of technicality
to refusing well.
Refusing artfully may diminish
the conflict,
but it does not resolve
the fundamental issue.
If you want to improve your reputation,
you need to be willing
to dedicate your time.
If you'd rather have time for yourself,
you shouldn't fret about your reputation.
(Sunim Laughter)
(Questioner) Thank you.